thank you hello everyone
so Mike and I'm here today to talk about
imperative development so I spent a lot
of time writing native modules and
extending react native and you know with
languages that are sort of less found in
JavaScript if you ask people on any meet
up like Objective C and those languages
are imperative and from the J's
community I've learned that imperative
is something bad something that I should
avoid and the code that I should be
writing some should be functional
declarative and pure it's not really
that true when we think in terms of
react native specifics and so the
purpose of this talk is to show you a
few use cases that I had some examples
and maybe the Mastiff itis fact that you
know in product is bad because it might
be actually a thing that you eventually
gonna use a like so why orchid call
stack which is company that I co-founded
and our mission is to help developers
and companies to run the wraps on all
the platforms and so it just happens to
the right now we are using react native
and since we are open-source enthusiasts
we are trying to contribute as much as
possible to the framework itself and by
going to conferences like this so if you
or your company is in need of some react
native help please reach out we'll be
more than happy to talk during this
conference so before we start let's do a
quick background check please raise your
hand if you have ever used react all
right I'm just testing if you are you
know gonna raise your head eventually
anyway so the real question is how many
of you know the difference between
imperative development and declarative
alright that's quite a few so let's do a
quick introduction anyway so that it's
easier to follow the slides long story
short in practice programming focuses on
how the change is going to happen right
and so you have this container that you
want to style so what you're gonna do is
you're gonna basically set every style
yourself line by line in this case
background wave and
so we give it a set of commands and you
expect the end result in return with
declarative approach on the other hand
you want your container you describe how
you want you your container to look like
and you don't think of how it's gonna be
painted on screen in our case that could
be react for instance where we describe
our render where we describe our kuraki
in render method and we expect the
framer to take care of that so the
difference between these two is that
instead of focusing on low level
implementation details like whether this
property is supported whether this is
going to be styled in that way or the
other we focus on the one we want to get
so we shift the responsibility from us
over to the framer girl library we trust
the library that the library will do its
job well and that gives you the
performant code and puts the focus on
the application development itself so
back to the title from urban dictionary
you know the new black is something cool
and new trend to follow and it's coming
from the fashion industry because black
is always you know in fashion so if
something is the new black it's
naturally going to be the cool thing but
interactive programming is not a new
thing right it used to be around for a
while the hardware implementation of
almost all computers are imperative all
hardware is designed to work that way
because it it sort of executed matching
code which is imperative and from the
low-level perspective the state of your
program is just memory and statements
that you write are the instructions that
imperatively tell the computer or the
processing unit what to do as a response
to what you want and if as a you know
the higher we go the more abstractions
are built on top like statements if if
statements and stuff like that so if
imperative programming is not a new
thing what is the title of my talk gonna
be about right so let's take a look a
closer look at one trend
that I've observed over the past few
years within our community and you will
hopefully have an answer one we once we
are done with this JavaScript ecosystem
compared to the others it's still
relatively young you know if we think of
reacting react native and the libraries
that we have and so we don't settle on
existing solutions we constantly keep
innovating right every once in a while
there is a new framework or a new
library that is about to change
something like we used to have Redux
now people are you know discussing
whether it's still the thing to go where
you know context was bad now it's not
that bad and stuff like that so it's
changing all the time as our use cases
change and so with our community hanging
out on mediums like Twitter that's the
place where we naturally share our
findings right when we find out
something really cool we post it on
Twitter like oh my god this is cool
library that I did please check it out
and that's what everyone does like we
check it out we install it we star it
and then we fill in backs and that's the
end of life cycle and then the other
developers on board the framework they
start following us and they see those
messages and they treat them as best
practices right so to give you a better
idea let's take a look at an example so
when I start when starting a reactor app
the problem most of the people are
having right now is what is the state
management solution going to be right we
are like oh should I use Redux should I
use mob X how many of you have a count
on a react Native community group on
Facebook are on that group yeah quite
not that many which is surprising
you should probably join this group if
you want to get first-hand announcements
as far as the library but if you check
this group many people are asking okay
what are the technologies that I should
use what are the frameworks that I
should use and so that state which is
built-in mechanism right to the react
like no one thinks about it it it is
sort of considered harmful right there
is even a lint rule that is you know
making such state like an error if you
use it so you might be wondering how
something such fundamental as stay
react can be an anti-pattern like is the
whole framework bad speaking in terms of
those people so the thing is developer
that is advertising his solution on
Twitter medium or any other place has
some project specific context in mind
like when I'm gonna be telling you that
like today those are the things that
worked for me
they might not work for you because I
was doing some very specific things at
job and those circumstances are really
important the problem is on Twitter the
context fades away especially you know
given the limit of characters it's like
when I write sad state is an
anti-pattern and I use some nasty click
bite strategies this is gonna be very
popular and no one will be talking about
the real thing that was at the end of my
article for instance so how many of you
are using sad state or state all right
so that's that that's a lot of people
and so then Abramoff said recently which
was a year ago
time flies or actually two it's okay and
when people say said state is an
anti-pattern
they mean a five hundred line components
with a complex says they supe scattered
across even handlers right so how many
of you would use state again after
reading this okay still few people but
less so that means you know by putting
the context necessary you wouldn't
probably use the state in such a big
component right all of you that are
using state we are probably talking of
small components like maybe holding
state of a button or a forum right but
not doing state for like a whole app two
thousand lines one file right because
this is what said state is considered an
anti-pattern this is where it shouldn't
be used so that is the context necessary
for this statement so there was a
similar trend in the past unfortunately
I couldn't find the original outdoor so
I just put myself there basically said
that imperative code is an anti-pattern
when I was working back in as a on on
Ashta which is a great library or
fully-fledged software development kid
Burma by my friend imperative code was
like considered an anti-pattern was very
popular and in that library we used to
have a lot of issues that oh this is
imperative this is not pure please
change it you know and stuff like that
and so if you are like me you are Greve
of this statement right because react
brought the clarity of approach it sort
of took away dumb api's and all that
you know stuff from us and gave us a
nice API to build apps so essentially I
would say this is right this is correct
and before I started doing react native
I was doing iOS development and so my
iOS code was all the way down imperative
like it was such a mess that I couldn't
even you know handle it myself after a
while especially the transitions and
stuff like that it was beautiful but it
was really messy so the purpose of this
talk is to show you that in context of
react imperative is not a bad thing but
it's actually something we should be you
know using cuz it powers a lot of
reactor native abstractions and is what
can take your react native development
to the next level in fact we already
talked about it you know native
platforms are in project by their design
right so react and react native have to
ship with those abstractions to handle
it just like on the web react is
wrapping gum api's for us using virtual
Dom and some clever algorithms to make
it performant same thing happens on
mobile when the react native is using
bridge to basically render our render
tree to objective-c and to Java controls
other rendered on ios and android right
and so it makes it very easy for regular
developer like me that doesn't know
Android to write Android app like the
first day that I sort of started doing
react native I felt like C or
development because you know after
struggling with iOS for like a month I
was able to do the same like a week on
both platforms and I was like Jesus
Christ like
that's that's the end of my career now
and so all thanks to abstractions the
other all thanks to you know modules
like animated react native gesture
handler the trap nest EAP ice and expose
a very nice interface for you to use and
over the course of past few years doing
react native I've discovered this
contract this relation between
imperative and declarative that is
within react and react native a
beautiful abstraction that can really
help you write really interesting
libraries so imperative code is
everywhere you know and there is no
reason to run away from it all the
declarative wouldn't be possible if
there wasn't imperative layer below it
so by learning how to use it you open
the doors to write performant apps and
api's and in this talk I want to show
you a real-life example that uses
imperative code to achieve something
that is not supported by react native I
mean it may sound crazy but it's it's
not really that crazy and demonstrate a
universal and flexible sort of approach
to writing such abstractions in the
future so react native ships with a lot
of great API s-- by default and if you
are using expo you even get more of them
but this pirates ecosystem getting more
and more stable and future reach it's
still there is still that need for
native modules and native code when you
are shipping something you may need to
wrap a proprietary API or maybe some
module that is not currently supported
well and so it's just good to have this
native hatch and be familiar with how
the native development works because
that's the way to ensure the long-term
stability of your app and what I also
like about this about writing native
code is that it broadens your horizons
back in a day I was like wondering every
every month because I've read somewhere
in an article that every developer
should learn at least one language per
year in order to stay up to date
something like this I'm not really sure
if that was proved or not I just read it
it sticks in my head for a while and so
for some reason I just couldn't make it
like I didn't have enough time and when
I started doing react native I got
really excited because I was sort of
forced to write three languages at a
time so that is really great because it
helps you to become a better developer
tool so you probably already guessed
that from the intro to native modules I
was challenged to write one that you can
see on the screen we've been talking
about this app quite a few times already
every time from a slightly different
perspective so if you will be interested
in to hearing more about that please let
me know it's a music app and on the
screen you can see a component that
renders full screen SVG with nodes and
each node on the screen has its
corresponding timestamp so that I know
that for instance the the one that is
already read should be highlighted at
for instance ten-second right and as the
music plays the SVG Scrolls and the
nodes are highlighting so we can think
of it as a nice timeline that is
scrolling as you play and the irr kita
architecture of this can be broken down
into few components and as I already
said we've been already talking about
few of them but today we are going to
focus on the playback service itself not
talking about animations performance and
all that stuff so first and foremost in
order to play the music we need a media
playback service right and a quick look
at existing react native api's reviews
there is nothing built-in right however
that doesn't mean it's impossible as I
said there is that escape hatch and it
just happens that both iOS and Android
have great libraries built-in by default
for the purpose of this talk I decided
to use streaming kit which is iOS
wrapper just because it's it's more
concise it has smaller syntax and will
be just easier to fit in slides so once
we know the libraries let's go ahead and
create native module that we will be
putting those methods inside and so I'm
not going to go into the header file
which is dot H because that's where the
definition is gonna be I'm gonna be in
the m file which is the place where I'll
be implementing my methods so what are
the most common actions the typical
media player should perform it's most
likely play right
Sanga resumed it to stop it and to play
next one right so free methods now to be
honest there are way more things that we
need to implement in order to make a
production ready player like
interruptions such as when someone is
calling you or you are listening to an
avocation directions or background modes
in this talk the focus is on the
framework itself if you are interested
feel free to ask me later about other
methods or generally what is the
approach to implement them so now that
we know them let's go ahead and start
writing some stuff I jumped too much
sorry if you are having latest mock you
probably know that it's sometimes
triggers double the the key press so
when I press space it skips many slides
very handy and so first thing is we have
to export the module itself right so we
got up with our city expert module
nothing fancy and then we're gonna
create an instance of the player that
will live throughout the life style
lifespan of this module now this is not
something that you usually do in your
yet another native module because this
one is overriding the constructor
basically what I'm doing is I'm just
setting a property audio player because
that's the most reasonable place where I
can put it and finally we can directly
expose play stop and and next on the
instance of the player and as you can
see I'm wrapping every midfield with our
city expert me forth which will make it
again available for the JavaScript to
call so this is very very low low-level
deep stuff on the native side which as
you can see is going to be imperative
because we are basically going play
datasource and stuff like that so it's
time to move one level up to the
JavaScript interface and we are going to
create a very simple JavaScript wrapper
with free methods to control the
playback and all the other methods that
we have created and those api's are
async and when cold will go over to the
bridge to talk to the native code we
just wrote right so to make it easier to
visualize the react component we will be
working on let's pretend that this is
the screen of the shiny new design that
is going to be the new Spotify and Apple
Musical 2
right and we would probably go ahead and
scaffold something like this on screen
that has the render me thought it's not
really important for case of the stock
so I'm just gonna make it empty with
free with free with free me first are
basically gonna call into the API that I
just created right so at this point we
have already created our module that is
impressively calling some some stuff
right when I press stop stop start stop
it will be basically working fine the
problem is as I started using this
coding to print in production I started
hitting a typical imperative issues that
normally we hit like async mass you know
like when I'm pressing stop stop stop
resume many times like I have no control
over the bridge how they're gonna be
going like some issues like that and
also the bigger problem was from the
long-term perspective that the
responsibility to implement the player
was on my team right so when I make the
library or whoever made the library I
just made I just made some building
blocks to compose the player but I
didn't do the whole logic so things like
interruptions background modes were
still left up to people that were just
interested in doing the playback service
right so you're shifting the
responsibility on them and they don't
necessarily have to know how to write
this so for instance the the basic
challenges are as I said interruptions
background mode maybe you want to
crucified them buffer up front things
like that an answers to the above
questions are not easy because it
doesn't really fit into react model
imperative code itself doesn't really
work with react because react is
declarative and so I started digging
around existing modules to understand
how react native team handled that
before which is actually an interesting
take away and every time you are
wondering how to implement something I
encourage you to go to react native
source code just look at something that
they did and it's a great resource of
learnings and interesting performance
optimizations that are not necessarily
documented in the documentation
so on my way to answer that problem
those problems I started you know
digging around statusbar API now if
you've been using react native before
you know that statusbar api used to be
imperative there used to be status bar
dot set style that changed to a
component so I felt like okay if the
team changed this API from imperative to
declarative there has to be a reason the
reason that that is very important for
my project as well so just to recap for
those who haven't used alt status bar
API this is how it used to be you were
basically calling such status bar style
you can technically still do it but it's
not a not a preferred way let's say but
now it's a component that you can embed
in your render hierarchy that will
basically adjust your status bar style
so that transition got me thinking why
it happened like what was wrong with the
existing approach and so turns out that
one of the most annoying go issues was
glitches that were happening because of
unpredicted calls because if you had
many screens with those calls in
component deep mild will update and
stuff like that it was basically
impossible for you to control how the
status bar is going to look like and it
started reminding me the issues that I
was running in so if my player so I
thought it's gonna be a good takeaway to
dig into that deeper and rewrite
component itself a bit and so I figure
out that the source of all the issues
and challenges as I said is the fact
that I'm using imperative itself which
is 50% off of the of the stuff it's not
like by making my library with that
imperative interface I only did half of
it the other thing that was missing was
the declarative facade like the
declarative interface the entry point
the public interface that will be for a
user is not for developers so I started
thinking in a declarative way what would
be the contract what would be the props
if my player was a component so
basically I figured the most two
important traps from my perspective are
going to be is playing and a song so in
order to get the music playing with the
aforementioned API all you have to do is
to place this
and anywhere in your render me fault and
going to the next song is also easy you
don't have to think about anything you
just basically to change the prop and
you are done so now that we know how the
declarative interface could potentially
look like let's take a look at how to
actually connect these two together so
from here on it's really easy if we
think of data source for this what is
the what is the source of true
those are the probes right and what is
the place in the react lifecycle where
we can listen for perhaps changing
inside our component will receive
perhaps or did update right in this case
I decided to use the update because I
will be calling bridge and so I don't
want to call before the update just in
case there's gonna be a precious
animation going on on screen and so this
is a very very damp copy-pasted function
from my production code that basically
shows how I'm reacting to those prop
changes imperatively under the hood as
you can see it may look dumb you may be
laughing that this is very very you know
stupid way of doing stuff but it really
works and as you go deeper as you start
adding features like crossfade buffering
and stuff it's really performant but
doesn't look like this at the beginning
which is a real beauty and so one bonus
point is that the current infrastructure
consists of a native module a J's rapper
and a react component so free files to
provide a very simple function and that
works for most of the time and most of
the use cases that you might have but
you can also create a native view
component where you can put all those
things together and so do you know
what's the difference between an ad view
component and a native module who knows
hands up alright so native module is
like a library right it's like a piece
of code that exposes some api's from
native to Jas so when you have a segment
for instance kit API which is for
tracking events you can export those
methods directly to Jas for something
that is called a native module and for
instance an example of a native module
from react native car would be alert iOS
would be that's a good example
an ad view component is something that
you put into your render method as a JSX
component and that's native code as well
an example is status bar status bar is
I'm not actually sure about but map view
for instance is a good example or scroll
view or actually any other one as well
and so it is different from a native
module that it defines this view method
here so in this case I'm defining this
view and basically this is gonna sell
react that okay if this native module is
rendered in react please get an instance
of view from this view me fat and put it
inside render method the rest of the
property stays the same so we still have
on progress song and playing props so
sort of direct direct corresponding prop
and then the implementation of this is
really simple or maybe not
don't get scared with the square
brackets of Objective C but as you can
see instead of component did update I'm
using this deed set perhaps me thought
which is exactly the same on iOS native
side of things it receives an object
that basically tells me what props did
change so I'm changing the playback and
a song based on the props up change and
now you may be asking like what's the
point of doing native view component if
it's like all that crappy Objective C
and you know it's hard to wrap our hands
heads around it as always its
performance so when you create a native
module the only way to pass an event is
through an even diameter right so if you
are creating a media player scroll view
whatever you basically gonna be emitting
events for the bridge as you omit those
events for the bridge you're you're
going to cause some traffic over the
bridge right and that combined with
animations or all the other stuff you
might be doing may cause your frames to
drop and so by defining a non progress
callback by using component instead of a
module I have this precious ability to
use animated that event and when I use
animated that event what it will do is
it will directly map
these dot state that progress which is
animated value with whatever value will
be from the on progress event now the
beauty is that if you set the use native
driver to true it will skip the bridge
so if you do sixty updates per second
which is what I was doing for the own
progress event because the music was
playing right you set this to true and
you can do whatever you want your app
feels native and there is no issue at
all so to sum up our work around the
module in order to make a performant
library that plays music or does any
other thing you have to create a
declarative interface that uses
imperative car under the hood to get
things done and also the benefit of this
is that you can make it make it
cross-platform right cuz on on web you
can use video in my case in your case
that could be a different API to get
things done so does it mean that
imperative is evil if we just created a
declarative interface to it it's not
really right it's a foundation that
react native is built on top and it's
what makes all the things possible that
we are using without the imperative code
it wouldn't be possible to do anything
like throw an alert use clipboard on the
react native launch any other apps and
stuff like this so I believe the API
design like that which is combining
declarative with imperative is the holy
grail of react native development
because imperative code is powerful but
it can be used very badly it can cause
you a lot of troubles if you overuse it
and react the react native are those
guards that give you tools to handle the
imperative code so I encourage you to
think of this pattern next time you are
about to write an API and who knows
maybe it will help you write a bear up
something more maintainable or basically
more advanced thank you very much
you
[Applause]